In the next video, we're going to install a virtual box hypervisor and then we're going
to set up a Linux Ubuntu virtual machine on it.
So if you have a Windows machine or Mac OS like I do, you can follow this tutorial to
set up a Linux virtual machine.
Now before we start installing the virtual box tool, I want to mention that in case you
have any issues during the installation, I actually added a section where I go through
some of the common issues that you may encounter during the installation, especially depending
on which operating system you're using an installing virtual box on and you may find
a solution there.
In this section, I want to go through some of the common issues that you may encounter
during the installation and I want to give you some options or alternatives to actually
fix those issues or install or create your virtual machine in a different way.
First of all, I want to start by saying that the main goal of the lecture is not to teach
you how to use virtual box or generally how the virtual machine installation works because
you won't actually be doing that so often as a DevOps engineer, so you don't need that
knowledge so much.
The main goal is to learn Linux.
So having a Linux machine available is actually the main focus of this lecture so you can
follow along the rest of the demos in this specific module.
Throughout the rest of the bootcamp, we're actually going to be working with cloud platforms
and creating virtual servers there, so you won't be working with virtual machines locally
after this module.
And this means if installing a virtual machine does not work or you have any issues during
this process, when you're following the demo that I'm showing you, don't spend too much
time on that.
You can either spin up a simple virtual machine on a cloud platform, which I actually teach
in the cloud basics module, and I'm going to link exactly the module and video number
below this video so you can find it directly, or if you don't want to pay the cloud platform
yet, and if you want to actually wait until we get to that module, you can spin up a virtual
machine for free on this online platform, and you will have a Linux Ubuntu machine available
through the browser.
And this is actually going to be the easiest option.
I will leave the link to this online platform below the video as well, so you will find
all this information there.
So basically find the easiest way to get a Linux machine and you are going to be good
to go.
If you already have a Linux distribution, and if you're working on a Linux computer
or laptop, you don't need to install any VM at all, you can skip this part, and you
can do the demos in the following videos with your Linux operating system.
I also want to mention that this is actually a very common issue with any technology or
tool, and it's a common problem in IT that we all have to deal with called version compatibility.
So in this case, you guys have different operating systems, different versions of operating systems,
different hardware resources, etc., so there is no one solution fits all.
So you may all have to do this in different ways.
And VirtualBox is actually the most standard tool across all operating systems, and that's
why I selected it, but it doesn't work for some specific cases.
For example, the latest Mac OS version is not supported yet by VirtualBox.
They will fix that in the future, but for now it's not working.
So that's again a typical version compatibility issue where the one tool hasn't caught up
with another tool yet.
So for those cases, I want to suggest some alternatives to follow the demos without getting
stuck here and interrupting your learning process.
So here are a couple of suggestions.
If you're on a Windows machine and the demo that I'm showing you is not working for you,
first of all, please make sure you have virtualization enabled in BIOS.
I will leave the resources below where you can see how that works for different Windows
versions.
And VirtualBox is actually the best VM tool for Windows, however, you will need some resources
on your computer.
And if you don't have enough CPU, enough RAM to allocate to your VM, then I suggest
you go with a less resource intensive option.
For example, you can install WSL, which is Windows subsystem for Linux, which will require
way less resources.
And again, I will leave the links below this video for guides of how to install WSL.
If you're on Mac, especially if you have the latest version of Mac OS operating system,
or if you have the latest Mac hardware with M1 chip, the VirtualBox installation is not
going to work for you.
So I suggest two easy and better alternatives.
The first one is installing UTM, that's a virtual machine tool for Mac OS, and another
one which is called Parallels.
They're both very easy to install and get started with.
And again, I will leave all the links that show you how to install each one of them below
this video.
Another issue with VirtualBox that some students also encountered is installing the extension
pack that basically lets you copy and paste between host and the virtual machine.
So that part is not working, or you're getting an error during the installation, please check
out the resource that I'm going to leave below this video for step by step guide of
how to fix that.
The final notes on resources.
As I also mentioned, many of you have different hardware resources.
Generally, the more RAM and CPU you allocate to your virtual machine, the faster and more
performant it is.
So if you do have enough resources, then increase RAM and CPU for your VM when you're creating
it.
But if you're working with limited resources, for example, Windows operating system itself
requires more resources than Linux, for example.
So Windows machines are usually slower because they already use up a lot of the resources.
So in that case, you may have some resource limitation.
As I suggested, in that case, please use some less resource intensive tool like WSL instead
of the VirtualBox or the online platform where you can spin up a virtual machine without
having to install it locally.
So overall, as I said, pick the easiest option and continue with the demos.
I usually say that if something is not working, you should play around with it.
This way you learn the tool better.
But local virtual machine installation is not that important of a use case.
So you can skip it and go with some easy option like the online virtual machine.
So you can proceed with your learning.
So first of all, we're going to need to download VirtualBox.
So in Google search box, I'm just going to type in VirtualBox download.
And we have this Oracle VirtualBox page.
And here you have the latest package for different operating systems.
So we have VirtualBox for Windows.
So if you're on Windows, now load this one.
I have Mac OS and that's the package I'm going to download.
So I'm going to click on install file.
And since it's over 100 megabytes, it may take some time to install.
Great.
Once that's done, I'm just going to click on that.
And this should present us with VirtualBox installation window.
And to install it, I'm just going to double click on it.
And we get this installation wizard.
So we're just going to click continue without changing anything.
Continue.
It tells you how much resources it's going to need on your computer.
We're going to do install and allow installing.
And installation was successful.
And that means we have VirtualBox now installed locally so we can use it.
Now if you're on Mac, actually, there is one thing that you may need to configure for
the VirtualBox installation to succeed.
So if your installment actually failed in the security and privacy settings here, you
may have a prompt here that says allow Oracle America basically to access your computer resources.
So you will need to allow that and then do the installation again.
So now I'm going to search for VirtualBox on my machine and you see that it is installed.
We have that application.
I'm going to click on it.
And we should see this VirtualBox manager window.
So basically we have this graphical user interface for VirtualBox to create the virtual
machines and to manage them, basically to change any settings on them, to remove them,
to create them, etc.
Which of course makes it easy to work with virtual machines.
Now one prerequisite that I want to mention here when you're creating virtual machines
on your computer is the prerequisite of resources.
So you are going to need at least four gigabytes of RAM on your computer because otherwise
you may have some problems creating virtual machine.
Because remember that we are sharing the hardware resources of the computer now among two computers.
So your operating system, your host operating system, in this case Mac, is already using
up some hardware resources and on top of that we're going to create another machine which
is going to require its own hardware resources.
And four gigabytes of RAM I would say is really the lowest limit.
So make sure you have that on your computer.
Great.
So next step is to actually prepare the environment for the virtual machine to be created.
And for that we're going to do new and we're going to set all this up.
And since we're creating a Linux virtual machine here let's call it Linux Ubuntu.
And you see that it basically intelligently detected from the name that I gave it that
we want Linux type of virtual machine here and version is Ubuntu 64 bit.
And this is basically where virtual machine will create the folders for the virtual machine
configuration.
And there is an option here to add an operating system ISO image to install on the virtual
machine.
We will leave this empty for now and upload the disk image after the VM is created in
virtual box.
And here is basically where we assign the virtual machine hardware resources.
So this is going to be a virtual RAM that our Linux VM will get.
And basically you can adjust this.
But again know that this shows you the entire RAM size that you have on your computer.
And now you have to share some of that with the VM.
I'm going to increase the allocated memory here to 4096 megabytes which is around four
gigabytes of memory which I'm going to give to my Linux VM.
It is also possible to allocate CPU resources to the virtual machine.
If you have enough computing power on your local computer you should actually allocate
four gigabytes of RAM and two CPUs to the virtual machine to avoid any performance issues.
And that is what I will do and then click next.
Here we will create a new virtual hard disk and we can adjust the virtual hard disk or
hard drive space size assigned to our VM.
The default option I have here is 25 gigabytes.
Although it is possible to allocate as little as 10 gigabytes I actually recommend allocating
at least 20 or even 30 gigabytes of storage if you have enough space on your host machine.
There is an additional storage option shown by the checkbox here next to preallocate full
size hard disk.
If you leave this box unchecked the hypervisor will actually intelligently decide how much
storage your virtual machine needs and basically dynamically set it.
So if it doesn't need 10 gigabytes of storage it's going to allocate less.
If it needs more storage it's going to request more storage from the host operating system.
If you select preallocated full size disk then it will be allocated the entire 25 gigabytes
and that's it.
We will leave the checkbox unmarked to set the storage to be dynamic and then click next.
The summary page will show you the settings you have chosen and you can click finish to
create the virtual machine.
Awesome.
So you see that we have Linux Ubuntu operating system and we have all the settings here,
the storage size, et cetera displayed.
Now what we did is actually prepare an environment for Linux virtual image to run on, right?
So this is like a container so to say where we're going to install Linux operating system.
So we need to actually install Linux operating system on this virtual machine and for that
we're going to need a Linux operating system image.
Just like you would take your laptop, your physical laptop and if you wanted to install
Linux Ubuntu or any other distribution on it you would have this Linux operating system
image on a USB or a disk or whatever and you would attach that to your laptop and you would
install that from that USB, right?
The same way we need a Linux image that we're going to install into our VM and those operating
system images usually have .iso extension ISO and if I type in Ubuntu downloads on
this website here ubuntu.com slash download you actually have all Ubuntu installation
images and here I want to mention that virtual box and Ubuntu they're both free or generally
Linux is free so basically we don't need any type of license we can just download them
and use them for free which is actually pretty amazing because if you want to use Windows
for example if you want to install Windows operating system in your virtual machine then
you would have to have a Windows license, right?
So in our case we're going to need Ubuntu desktop because I want to have a graphical user interface
in my Ubuntu installation so I'm going to click on it and on this page we're seeing the Ubuntu
versions that we can download we have the latest one which is 22.10 and we have a slightly
older version 22.4 which has the letters LTS at the end so LTS basically stands for long
term support and this means that this specific version is actually the one now which will
be supported by the Ubuntu team or Ubuntu developers so usually you want to download
the versions that are supported by the developers of the technology and I'm just going to click
on download and it should start automatically and as I said it has the ISO extension so
basically you could use this Linux Ubuntu installation file to install Linux on a virtual
machine but also on a physical laptop, right?
So if you wanted to install this on your computer directly without the hypervisor you would actually
use the same ISO image and the ISO file is around 3 gigabytes which means it might take
a while to download and I have the Ubuntu installer on my laptop so we can actually
use it now.
I'm going to go back to my virtual box window and if you click settings and then storage
you're able to select the icon next to the optical drive to upload your operating system
image to be installed so I'm going to click here and select choose disk file and we're
going to select this ISO image that we downloaded once we have added this image we can start
the virtual machine and as you see Ubuntu installation is actually starting and now
we have this step by step installation guide where you basically choose your language and
different configurations like your time zone etc to install Ubuntu.
So we have English here we're going to do install Ubuntu and again choose the language
I'm going to choose German because that's my keyboard layout and continue I would leave
everything on the defaults continue and here you see this warning that says that erase
disk and install Ubuntu option will basically delete all your programs documents photos
whatever in all operating systems.
Now don't be afraid of this warning because the disk that this refers to is actually the
virtual disk that we allocated to our VM right so our main operating systems disk will not
be affected this is really only the part that we allocated for VM which means that erasing
that virtual disk will not affect our main host so you don't need to worry here and
the reason you have this warning and it sounds so scary is because as I said this installation
image is actually also for the physical computers right not only for virtual machine installations
so obviously on a physical machine where you're installing it on your whole computer without
a hypervisor then you may consider the warning that everything will be erased on your computer
in our case we are starting with a blank virtual disk anyways so it doesn't matter and I'm
going to do install now and again we have this dialogue do you really want to change
or rewrite the disk to be really sure as I said this is just a virtual disk so go for
it and continue that's my location and now we're going to create the linux user and let's
call it nana.buntu password and I'm going to check login automatically and continue and
while it's installing and downloading different stuff it actually shows you all these things
that you can install additionally like music players and some other applications but we're
not going to need any of those and as I mentioned previously this linux operating system that
we're installing now on virtual machine doesn't actually know that it's on a virtual machine so
everything that it does is exactly the same way as you would install linux operating system on
an actual physical machine so the steps are really the same so installation completed and we're
actually good to go I'm going to restart while the VM is restarting remove the disk image now
that the installation is complete click devices optical drive and remove and we should see Ubuntu
desktop in our virtual machine window I'm gonna do skip and next you need to confirm some settings
here and we're good to go so basically have all these applications that are installed by default
including a Firefox browser and the linux command line now first of all you see that the input
output devices like obviously the screen but also mouse and keyboard they're all responsive here so
basically you are sharing these resources also between your main operating system so you can use
it here but also inside the virtual machine however other than that everything is completely
isolated so whatever is running inside and whatever we're doing here is completely hidden and
isolated from the host operating system so before we continue with linux let's actually see some of
the other options that we can set on our virtual machines from the virtual box so first of all if
I want to shut down my virtual machine I have several options one of them is saving the machine
state so that means that basically whatever state you were in for example you have a browser open
here with some tabs you have terminal window open maybe you have an editor where you are writing
some code you can basically save that state so all these open tabs like this so after some time if
you want to go back to your virtual machine and basically continue working then you can just
click start and you're gonna see your virtual machine window exactly as you left it another
option is just powering off the machine which basically just shuts down your virtual machine
it's basically just like shutting down your computer right so doing a basic shutdown here
another thing that may be very interesting especially if you're using the virtual machine to
basically learn something you may want to be able to copy and paste between your host and the virtual
machine and as I said the mouse and keyboard is active in both by default you can basically just
copy a text here and paste it in a virtual machine window it's not gonna work however you can
actually enable that in the settings advanced and right here shared clipboard so you can basically
set this so that you can only copy stuff from the host to the guest vice versa or you can do it by
directional and as I said this will make it convenient if you want to basically copy some
commands that you have on your operating system editor whatever and you want to basically just
paste in a terminal or maybe you have a link that you want to open in the browser here so then
may be convenient so I'm actually gonna select that and save it however for this bi-directional
clipboard sharing to work we first have to install something called an extension pack for the virtual
box so if we go back to this virtual box downloads page we have for the same version that we
installed here we have a VM virtual box extension pack and there is one installer for all the
platforms so we're gonna click on that and download so basically it's a small extra package that
lets you add some functionality to your virtual box so I'm gonna click on it and install and agree
on the licensing and there you go the extension pack was successfully installed however there is
one final thing we need to do here so that the copy pasting can work so I'm gonna open the virtual
machine first and right here on the top you have a couple of options one of them is devices and here
we have something called guest additions so guest additions package is actually the one
specifically enabling this copy paste or drag and drop functionality and if I click on insert
guest additions CD image to run the installer script open the contents of the disk drive right
click order on dot sh and select run as program authenticate so the guest additions installer
ran we can click to return and if I click on here you see this is the folder actually where all
these runners and installers are located and we can unmount it and now let's actually test the
functionality so I'm gonna copy the URL from my host and try to paste it right here and there you
go and the same way you can paste commands from your host machine to the terminal so if I'm reading
a tutorial and if I found some really large command that I don't want to type in I can just copy it
here on my host again back to the terminal paste and there you go so that's how you set up clipboard
sharing between the host and the virtual machine this is very convenient if you're learning or
testing out stuff in your VM another thing which is also very interesting is that by default virtual
machine actually runs in its own virtual network which is completely isolated from your host's
network right so your laptop your computer is running on your home network however the virtual
machine is not in that same network and if you actually scanned all the devices on your home
network you won't see your virtual machine on it and the same way if someone accessed your virtual
machine's network and basically hacked into it they won't be able to access your home network
because again they're isolated which is good for security and that's how it's set by default however
you can also change that and basically add your virtual machine to the same network as your host
operating system so it's gonna get an IP address within the same network and you can change that
settings in the network tab here however we don't need that so we're gonna leave that at the default
and there are some other things that you can basically share between the host and the guest
operating system like shared folders etc just note that when you start basically sharing stuff
between the host and guest operating systems like sharing files and folders and basically this clipboard
and sharing network it may be convenient because you may have use cases for that however in that
case we're gonna be making holes in this isolation between the host and guest operating systems right
which is great because the guest operating system cannot affect the host the main operating system
because they're completely isolated however if you start sharing resources then you are disrupting
that complete isolation so just important to be aware of that so with this type of sharing and the
settings you may be compromising security in our case the only thing we shared is clipboard and
everything else will stay the same and since we have linux want to set up in the next video we're
gonna go through linux operating system and learn some basics of it starting with the linux file system